I need to tell this story. I need to get it out of me. It happened when I was in the military,
and I did something bad because it was the right thing to do. And it bothers me,
but I can't tell people about it. It could get other people in trouble. And myself, I suppose.
Amp BI was an ER nurse on a military base. There was an accident during training. Yes,
it happened all day every day, but this one, it was a flight incident.
Flight incidents are a big deal. People die and multi-million dollar aircraft are destroyed.
This accident was no different. My patient was the pilot, who ejected and lived. Others did not,
and the accident was considered my patient's fault. Amp XB, so they bring the guy in.
He walked in, he was fine, racked with survival guilt, sure, and we had to do the whole trauma
x-ray thing. But I was the highest ranking nurse in the ER that day. For that reason,
the flight incident documentation was tasked to me. And I was to perform the mandated chain of
custody blood draw to test the pilot for drugs or alcohol. Amp XB, the room was somber. There had
been deaths today. Deaths of people who were close to each other like brothers. The pilot's entire
squadron, all his bosses, his boss's bosses, were there. They passed through, and a couple sat with
him the whole time. Amp XB, I drew his blood. It's a chain of custody, which means every person who
touches the vials has to sign with a hand-off to it each hand-off. It's for legal purposes,
to verify that no one tampered or switched out a vial. I don't know why, but I drew excess blood.
Probably because it was my habit to draw a vial or two extra, in case a doctor wanted to add tests
so I wouldn't have to stick a patient with a needle twice. I had two extra vials. When I
gathered my trash up, I put them in my pocket. I don't know why, I usually would have just thrown
them away. But I had them, on my person. When the pilot was discharged, Amp XB's friends and
co-workers took him from our site to the nearest bar, to get immediately wasted and begin to grieve.
I don't know whether or not this is normal, or standard operating procedure, or even sanctioned
by the military. But whatever, his squadron went and got drunk together as they attempted to pull
the pilot from an abyss of self-blame. I suppose it is important when that's your job to get past
it so you can fly again, and I'm not going to judge anyone for how they managed to do that.
It's got to be difficult, going back to work, with the same people, all of you knowing you
were piloting during an accident that killed other people. So, yeah, they get a pass to go
get Blackout drunk from me. Amp XB but not an hour after they left, the lab called me.
There was a problem. The chain of custody blood draws needed drawn again. Someone had dropped the
first ones on the floor. Smashed into a million pieces, was my pilot's clean blood test. Now he
was at a bar, getting drunk, and I had to call him and have him come in to get a new blood draw.
It would not be clean. He would have alcohol in his blood. But I still had to have him come in.
Amp XB everyone understood the ramifications of what was happening. With alcohol in his blood
sample that was taken for his flight incident, he would be court-martialed. There would be a trial,
he would get charges, and he would do time in the brig. His commanding officer came with him.
I don't remember if he had a star or two or a bird. But his expression was grave.
The pilot's fate, I believe he was thinking, was sealed. Unless he, himself, told the truth,
that this was a redraw. That it happened well after the pilot was off duty. That he had begun
drinking to ease his grief and was called back. But that meant the flight incident report had no
blood draw. That would end this pilot's career. With whether or not he was drunk or on drugs
during the incident up in the air, he would be grounded. Possibly indefinitely, he would have
to crawl his way back up to where he was trusted to fly again. If he was elite, or wanted to be an
elite pilot, that's the end of the dream. Walking the pilot into the room where I was drawing his
blood was like walking a career to the gallows. Amp XB the whole time I did the paperwork and
drew the blood, I knew what I had to do. The commanding officer stammered and said things
and made explanations. I don't know what he thought I could do about the situation.
Im pretty sure he had no idea that I could or would do.